<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Neurosponge - misc</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2016-08-29T13:57:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Cycling the Cabot Trail 2016</title><link href="/cycling-the-cabot-trail-2016.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-29T13:57:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-08-29T13:57:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Neurosponge</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-08-29:/cycling-the-cabot-trail-2016.html</id><summary type="html">Trip report of a 5 day cycle tour through the Cabot Trail in Cape Breton</summary><content type="html">

    &lt;p&gt;One of the benefits of being a grad student is the opportunity to travel to other universities for the occasional workshop or retreat. This summer, in the twilight of my MSc., I was fortunate enough to get such an opportunity, a &lt;a href="radiant.com"&gt;summer entrepreneurial fellowship &lt;/a&gt; at Dalhousie University in Halifax. Awesome! A chance to get outside of the lab. Also, a great excuse for an outdoor trip. I took some time off after the fellowship to cycle the Cabot Trail and thought I'd share my experience in order to give some information to others thinking about making the trip themselves (which I heartily recommend!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure style="margin-top: 0px !important"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img alt="My route around the Trail. Stars indicate the locations of certifiably delicious restaurants." src="images/bikeroute.jpg" width="100%" align="center"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;My route around the Trail. Stars indicate the locations of certifiably delicious restaurants.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cabot trail is a 300km loop that winds around the northern part of Cape Breton, including the Highlands National Park and several small communities. The majority of the trail is a well-paved two-lane highway with only moderate traffic (mostly tourists in the Summer). The trail is unrelentingly hilly, especially in the park. Two mountain climbs (French Mt., North Mt.) present a significant uphill challenge that is best met with low gears and a firm resolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By reading several &lt;a href="http://travellingtwo.com/13565"&gt; trip&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.your-nova-scotia-holiday.com/cycling-the-cabot-trail.html"&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt; posted around the web, I decided to tackle the trail in the clockwise direction. Supposedly, this ensures more favourable wind conditions, but I can't say I benefitted in any particular way from the wind; it seemed to be against me as often as with me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I kept my riding distances under 80km per day and set a flexible schedule. In order to give some kind of order to my trip, I &lt;a href="https://support.google.com/maps/answer/6291838"&gt;downloaded the Google Map&lt;/a&gt; of the entire area and marked the locations of all the campgrounds and restaurants I thought I might want to visit. Didn't need a physical map. This all worked out really well, though of course I didn't get to every thing I had marked. I made it around the trail in 5 days, sore and satisfied when it was over, but could see the trip could be shortened to just 3 days or stretched to 6 or more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Day One: Halifax to Margaree&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's worth mentioning how the trip officially began in Halifax -- grabbing shuttle bus from Halifax. I went with the &lt;a href="http://www.scotiashuttle.ca/"&gt;Scotia Shuttle&lt;/a&gt; company. I'd recommend them if you're looking for a way to get a bike up to Cape Breton. They were friendly, punctual, affordable, and best of all, able to fit my bike and all my gear in the back of their van.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shuttle took around three hours, placing me in Baddeck at noon. I immediately found my way to &lt;a href="http://visitbaddeck.com/bean-there-cafe/"&gt;Bean There Cafe&lt;/a&gt;, where I caught up on a missed breakfast, double-checked my maps, and gathered courage (read: coffee). The forecast at the time predicted a thunderstorm touching down around six, so I, like a responsible adult, called ahead and reserve at a campground I knew I could reach before then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although most people start and end the Cabot Trail in Baddeck, the trail's two entrance points are actually a little bit outside of town. In order to get to the beginning of the trail heading clockwise, you have to head out from Baddeck on Margaree road. Maybe 2km in, Margaree becomes a dirt road (it's gorgeous, though). And here, surrounded by wild shrubbery and getting a feel for my bike's laden heft, I realized that the forecast I had seen earlier was definitely exactly 6 hours off. First there was drizzle, then, as I got to the &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt; part -- climbing up the Hunter Mt. -- a straight-up downpour. I cursed and shouted as I rode, terribly alone. It was just me and a bunch of wet plants. I cranked up the dharma talk in my headphones and by the time I started descending the mountain I was completely soaked and enjoying myself tremendously. My drenched t shirt lashed at my sides as I bombed the mountain. I felt free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this drenched, blissed-out state, arriving at the &lt;a href="thelakesresort.com"&gt;Lakes Campground&lt;/a&gt;, where I had planned to wait out the storm, was bittersweet. I was soaked beyond care and could have kept riding, but I &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; pretty hungry. I walked through the entrance sheepishly, summoning puddles. Fortunately, the Lakes' caretakers were incredibly friendly and accomodating. They let me dry off in the restaurant, served me up a "Big Boy" bacon cheeseburger, and even threw some of my wet clothes into the dryer downstairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Big Boy burger. Filled me up, as promised" src="images/bigboy.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Lakes' Big Boy burger. Filled me up, as promised&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Day Two: Margaree to Corny Creek&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a quick walk around the campground's premises, I set off again around 9:30. It was still drizzling and overcast, but the stretch of riding I did this morning wound up being one of my favorites. Between Middle River and Margaree (the town), the land opens up the north of the trail, revealing gently rolling farmland and green, mist-wreathed mountains, like what I imagine Ireland looks like. I picked up on a sense of something ancient and magical here and my thoughts drifted  back the Tolkien-inspired fantasy headspace of my childhood. The pleasantness of this morning was also enhanced by a quick break to gather courage at the &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/DancingGoatCafe/"&gt;Dancing Goat Cafe&lt;/a&gt;, where I ran into an infectiously happy, giddy group of retirees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="The agrarian, irish-seeming landscape of the south Cabot Trail" src="images/irishseeming.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The agrarian, irish-seeming landscape of the south Cabot Trail&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the ocean appeared, making its presence felt with prickly buffets. The level of moisture in the air picked up and a fierce wind blew from the west. Cycling in this started feeling pretty heroic. A windward bluff provided shelter for lunch -- two instant ramen packets  -- and gave me a chance to glimpse the ocean churning from on high. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style="margin-top: 2cm; margin-bottom: 2cm"&gt;
&lt;div style="position:relative;padding-bottom:57%"&gt;&lt;iframe src="https://gfycat.com/ifr/WhimsicalDeepAsp" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" width="100%" height="100%" style="position:absolute;top:0;left:0;" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I settled into a groove on the way to Cheticamp. The rugged coastline provided incredible scenery, as did the numerous quaint, Acadian homes dotting the landscape. Every one who lives around here seems to be named Aucoin or LeBlanc...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Cheticamp, I visited a grocery store (big Co-op on the trail, can't miss out) to pick up food and eavesdrop on the local's mixed conversations. I swear I could hardly understand a word of their French. What an accent, yeesh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stretch between Cheticamp and the Highlands park was idyllic. The trail rolls through pleasant rural properties and over a river, similar to a lot of other charming places on the trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I got to the Highlands Nation Park I knew I was in for a treat. Here, the land becomes mountainous with enormous, exposed cliffs rising up out of the sea. I'd go so far as to say it's the East Coast's compelling competitor to Big Sur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the most of the day, I headed down to a beach just after 'La Grande Failaise'. Totally beautiful, this beach, in the fading daylight. There are two rock monoliths to the south end of a mixed rock and a classically sandy beach. I found a perch on a little bluff and settled in for a pre-dinner snack as I watched the tourists spill in. There was a particular sense of superiority I enjoyed as a bike tourist, watching the bovine, selfie-stick-toting throng spill out of their rented luxury SUVs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style="margin-top: 2cm; margin-bottom: 2cm"&gt;
&lt;div style="position:relative;padding-bottom:57%"&gt;&lt;iframe src="https://gfycat.com/ifr/FrankCriminalBlueshark" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" width="100%" height="100%" style="position:absolute;top:0;left:0;" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After the beach, I packed up my bike and continued to the Corney Brook campsite. Luckily, I was able to grab the last open site here and treat myself to an extra large macaroni and cheese dinner: elbows, Edam cheese, garlic butter, classic camping food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Day Three: Over French Mt. to Pleasant Bay&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the third day I tackled French Mt., the highest point on the Cabot Trail. No easy feat, but coming from South it was more of just a really long slog as opposed to being unpleasantly steep. My &lt;a href="http://allcitycycles.com/bikes/space_horse"&gt;Space Horse&lt;/a&gt; nailed the climb. Halfway up, I was passed by a spritely, athletic-looking, tanned group of seniors on road bikes. One of them took a break with me (for cameraderie or pity I do not know) and offered me a delicious Israeli energy bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="Halfway up French Mt." src="images/frenchmt.jpg" width="100%" align="center" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Halfway up French Mt.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the summit of French Mt., I decided to hike the Skyline trail, without a doubt the park's most popular trail. Tons of people on it. The trail's nice -- cool views of wind-swept peaks at the end and a few km of an ecologically interesting grassland (the result of a 1970s bug infestation) slowly being reclaimed by trees. This apparently provides the perfect environment for moose, which makes sense cause I saw one! Right up close! Holy shit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="A bull moose grazing on saplings" src="images/moose.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A bull moose grazing on saplings&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After checking out the Skyline, I went on to visit "the Bog" and Benji's Lake. Both were great, especially so because of the incredible variety of unusual plants. The young deer ferns that lined the Benji's Lake trail  were so soft and such an alluring shade of green that I wished I was a moose, capable of grazing. Also really cool were the carnivorous sundew plants (&lt;em&gt;Drosera rotundifolia&lt;/em&gt;) in the Bog and along the edge of the Lake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="A sundew" src="images/sundew.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A sundew. They trap flies with little globs of glue secreted by their leaves!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Continuing down the trail (man, it is so fun to bike around the top of this mountain!), I eventually ran into some construction, which was holding up traffic for a little while. This forced me into a social encounter with two other cyclists on the trail: Zoe and Jeshi. I felt like a cycling amateur when I learned where they'd come from. Jeshi had ridden all the way from Maine and Zoe had started cycling in Vancouver(!) and was days away from ending her cross-Canada road trip in St. John's. They both had that serene come-what-may attitude of people who've been on the road a long time&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="So much fun to bike around up here" src="images/mtroad.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;So much fun to bike around up here&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The descent down French Mt. was a basket of anxiety. The road zig zags back and forth quite a bit, so one has to lay on the brakes at nearly every moment to avoid careening into the guard rail at high speed. There were ecstatic moments, but it was mostly a white knuckle brakefest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For dinner that day I visited the Rusty Anchor. It's quite the tourist feature, but I figured I might as well splurge for the experience. 50/50 Lobster/Crab Roll. Fantastic Dish. The lobster was better than the crab, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="50/50 Roll at Rusty Anchor. The Lobster was better by far" src="images/lobsterroll.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;50/50 roll at Rusty Anchor. The Lobster was excellent.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent this night at the MacIntosh Brook campground, which was absolutely lovely. There's a wide open grass field next to a stream and even a cabin with a stove, water, and electricity to charge the gadgets. I happened into Zoe and Jeshi here, as well as two other bike tourists from Montreal. We spent the evening hanging out, trading stories and discussing MSc. thesis projects until we turned in for bed at geriatric 9:30pm.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Day Three: MacIntosh Creek to Ingonish Beach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a communal coffee-filled morning in which I shared the francophones my &lt;a href="http://campingwithgus.com/2011/10/16/cowboy-coffee/"&gt;cowboy coffee technique&lt;/a&gt; we all set off to tackle North Mt. This one was wicked -- shorter, but much steeper than French. Plus, there was little shade and temperatures that climbed to nearly thirty degrees. A lot of breaks, spin class-level exertion, and hollering got me to the top, eventually. Topping out was momentous. My sweat cooled in the wind during the downhill stretches after the peak, which were fucking &lt;em&gt;great.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="Jeshi on the downhill after the peak of North Mt." src="images/jeshi.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Jeshi on the downhill after the peak of North Mt.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a long run-out from North Mt., I stopped to grab a cone at little art and ice cream store. There's advertisements for &lt;a href="https://scotsburn.com/"&gt;Scotsburn&lt;/a&gt;, some kind of Maritime ice cream brand everywhere. I had to try some. Being hungry and exhausted certainly must have had to something to do with how transcendent this experience was. Consuming a cone of chocolate ice cream in a field, I became one with the murmur of the crickets, the peeling paint of the gift shop, and the heat of the sun, everything in its right place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long after the ice cream stop, I ran into Zoe and Jeshi again (hard to keep eager, distractable cycle tourists together it turns out) at a general store in Cape North. I stopped with them and had a lunch of fried clams (not too impressive; they didn't taste like much besides "deep fried"). I got the sense this place was a real fixture of the community. The food was cheap and it was packed. A local lady with a dog recommended the breakfast sandwiches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My next stop was the Chowderhouse in Neil's Harbour. As a fan of chowder, I was looking forward to it when planning my trip. However, I found it packed full of tourists when I arrived around 2pm and didn't have that much of an appetite due to the ice cream and clams (who would have guessed?). I used the bathroom and nipped out. Neil's Harbour had a really nice lighthouse, despite it being overcast. I find there's just something really depressing about the beach when it's overcast &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt="The lighthouse in Neil's Harbour. It was overcast when I was there. I find there's just something really depressing about the beach when it's overcast" src="images/lighthouse.jpg" width="100%/"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Lighthouse at Neil's Harbour.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I found the next stretch, between Neil's Harbour and Ingonish, especially difficult. This was my most grueling day and the wear and tear of cycling had started to set in a little bit -- a touch of tendonitis in the achilles and a slight resurgence of patellofemoral in my right knee pain. Halfway up the last hill before Ingonish (unbeknowst to me at the time), I pulled over and sprawled beside the road, taking a much-needed rest. The concerned drivers who pulled over to check on me reassured me in the essential decency of humanity.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having skipped the Chowderhouse, I was planning on stopping at the Seagull restaurant to refuel. However, it was closed that day so I opted for the Coastal Waters Restaurant just down the way. It was a real "bar and grill" type place with beer artifacts on the walls and a little bit of a biker vibe. The fish and chips here were pretty damn good. Plus, they were playing &lt;a href="unionduke.com"&gt;Union Duke&lt;/a&gt; on the speakers (a local Toronto band), so I figure they're alright.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To finish the night, I visited Ingonish Beach and made sure to bathe in both the ocean and the lake that was right next to it. This was extremely refreshing. Even if you're sore and limping around from being on the bike all day you can still swim. After my dip, I settled in for the night at the Ingonish Beach Campground. Note: Ingonish Beach has an entry booth that was manned until 10pm and a heavy ranger presence. Keep that in mind if you're used to being able to dirtbag your way in for free.  &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Day Four: Ingonish Beach to St. Anne's Bay&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hustled out of the campground early to have breakfast somewhere a little bit more scenic. I settled on a ledge overlooking the ocean and prepped myself for more riding as groundskeepers for the Ingonish Beach golf course proceeded past me to their duties. Oatmeal with peanut butter and more cowboy coffee did the trick. I felt so perked up I decided to take a selfie. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="Feeling happy after four days of camping" src="images/selfie.jpg" style="width: 50% !important" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Feeling happy after four days of camping&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail following Ingonish Beach winds around Ingonish Harbour, perhaps the most scenic area in the group of "Ingonish" locations. Google had made predictions of heavy rain later in the day, but the morning sky was clear and brilliant and I enjoyed the wetlands surrounding the harbor. In one of the neighborhoods surrounding the harbor I came across a blueberry stand and picked up some jam that became a huge hit when I combined it with the peanut butter, apple, and raisin bread sandwiches I had been routinely consuming.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew there was one more big hill I to overcome -- Cape Smokey -- so I quickly caffeinated with another cup of coffee at the Knotty Pine Cottages general store, where I hit upon the news that a church a bit further down the road on St. Anne's Bay would host a &lt;em&gt;Ceilidh&lt;/em&gt; that night. I'd heard about these things (pronounce &lt;em&gt;Kay-lease&lt;/em&gt;) from multiple sources and wanted to check one out. Apparently, they're traditional gaelic musical gatherings.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cape Smoke's climb turned out to be no problem. Maybe I got stronger. However, I was surprised by how awesome the descent was. Unlike the previous two mountains, the road does not zig zag back and forth the whole way. Instead, there's a cpp; mixture of tight and broad turns, with more space to safely gain speed. There's even a S-curve near the end that you can take pretty fast. When I got to the bottom, I almost contemplated going back up to bomb it again. It was that fun.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="Top of Cape Smokey. Killer downhill after this" src="images/smokey.jpg" width="100%" align="center" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Top of Cape Smokey. Killer downhill after this&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Cape Smokey, I hit up the Dancing Moose Cafe for lunch. I hadn't been planning on visiting this spot, but the caretaker at Knotty Pine had specifically recommended their bacon-baked-inside pannekoken. Intriguing. Bacon Apple Raisin pannekoken ended up exceeding all my expectations. So good, I hung out for a few hours and also tried their lobster chowder -- incredible. Creamy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The young guy waiting tables at the Moose (obviously the owners' kid) told me about a beach I could visit a few km down the road, a place where there was also a wharf for professional lobster fisherman. I couldn't miss the opportunity to see a real maritime crustacean operation, so I headed down to the Little River Wharf after lunch. I didn't hang around too long (it was overcast), but I did see several guys pull up in trucks and fuss with boats that were anchored at the wharf. Lobster carcasses were littered around in unusual places.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not too long after the Wharf, right in Indian Brook, more construction began. This time it was a bit of a bummer as there was a long stretch of grooved road that wasn't the most pleasant to ride over. I rode on, doing my best to dodge the multitudes of caterpillars inching their way across the highway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite my best efforts to kill time at the Moose, I arrived at St. Ann's Bay United Church (where the &lt;em&gt;Ceilidh&lt;/em&gt; was due to take place), several hours early. After another round of sandwiches and coffee, I did what I thought was best -- take a nap in the forest. I hiked a bit down the Red Island Trial located next to the church and settled down with my sleeping pad as a pillow. I was woken once by a red(?) squirrel screaming from a few meters behind me and once by a group of kindly old ladies passing through the trail I was reclined out next to.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as the &lt;em&gt;Ceilidh&lt;/em&gt; started, I knew I was in for something special. First off, there was almost no one anywhere close to my age. Besides a few kids, everyone appeared to be over the age of 65, and it was clear everyone knew each other. The musicians that were playing were a local Cape Breton family -- husband, wife, and daughter and, as it turned out, the audience happened to be filled with members of their extended family. I saw enough hugs, kisses, and love-filled glances that I started thinking fondly on my own mom. I stepped outside only to realize that I was out of range of cellphone reception.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here was a real Cape Breton community assembled over music, singing songs about the area where they lived and the lives of their ancestors. There was nothing staged about this. It had the character of a jam session breaking out at a family reunion. The palpable sense of community generated by a bunch of relatives still living in a tight-knit way made me think about what our generation, with its diaspora -- ubiquitous plans to move away from home and study or find a career -- is giving up. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style="margin-top: 2cm; margin-bottom: 2cm"&gt;
&lt;div style="position:relative;padding-bottom:57%"&gt;&lt;iframe src="https://gfycat.com/ifr/ZestyLoneBirdofparadise" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" width="100%" height="100%" style="position:absolute;top:0;left:0;" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the show, I was warm and content enough to settle down anywhere for the night. I chose a spot in the woods near the trail where I had napped earlier. No campground needed, just a soft, loamy spot in the woods. I had a night of deep, peaceful sleep with colorful, thoughtful dreams, the best I had on the whole trip.  &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Day Five: Back to Baddeck and Big Spruce Brewing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The realization that I had scant amount of time left in Cape Breton was counterbalanced by the beauty of my surroundings when I woke up this last morning. It's very comfortable to wake up completely by oneself, far away from the activity of others. I took a hike down to the end of the trail as the sun rose above the trees, noting the many varieties of mushrooms that sprang out of the earth.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="The scene around my campsite in the morning" src="images/forestmorning.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The scene around my campsite in the morning&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the words of the musicians I met at the &lt;em&gt;Celidh&lt;/em&gt; last night in my head, I made sure to soak up as much nature as I could. When I passed the beautiful North River, a few km down the road, this meant stripping off my clothes and plunging in for a late-morning bath.

&lt;div style="margin-top: 2cm; margin-bottom: 2cm"&gt;
&lt;div style="position:relative;padding-bottom:57%"&gt;&lt;iframe src="https://gfycat.com/ifr/MatureRemoteCopepod" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" width="100%" height="100%" style="position:absolute;top:0;left:0;" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's always a hesitation in the mind about committing to cold water and, though I pride myself on being the type of person who is good at overcoming this, I always battle with the old familiar fear. The scene was so inviting that there really was no question about it this time. Plus, the North River is the last proper river crossing along the trail before Baddeck. Of course, all my hesitation was proved to be folly as soon as I got in the water. All remaining traces of my morning groggines were washed away and I felt better than ever.  &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This inland road, the last stretch of the Cabot Trail that winds along the inner part of St. Anne's Harbour was certainly one of the highlights of the trail for a cyclist. The Highlands are visible to the North, but gone are the steep hills. Here, there's only a gentle, manageable peaks and dips, so one can really gain some consistent speed on the bike. This area is also noticeably less populated than the other areas of the trail; no ice cream stores and art gallerys, just small, quaint, retirement homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get back to Baddeck at this point, you have to take highway 105 for a while. This is a bit of drag as it's nothing more than biking on the shoulder of a multi-lane highway, with cars and trucks passing you at the 90-110km/h speed range. However, once you get on route 205 back to Baddeck, there is a welcome return to picturesqueity. Winding along the edge of the Bras D'Or Lakes(s?), I ran into some classic maritime scenery here: sailboats, lightouses, reeds, diving birds, and flower gardens. At this point, I was really keen to settling into a cycling groove, relax, and soak it all in.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="Absurdly picturesque maritime views near Baddeck" src="images/Baddeck.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Absurdly picturesque maritime views near Baddeck&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, I made it back to downtown Baddeck and the familiar old Bean There Cafe. A celebratory coffee and social media binge then, I was back on the highway en route to my real end destination -- the Big Spruce Brewing Company. Their brewery, taproom, and hopyard is just 15km down the highway from Baddeck. I had had their beer at the Stubborn Goat in Halifax and was honestly a bit blown away -- I didn't foresee such good beer coming from such a remote place. At some point along the trail I developed the idea that a few pints of IPA would be the perfect end to my odyssey. And it was! Their HQ was just what I was hoping for: a spacious, outdoor patio with which to enjoy the 6 different beers they had fresh on tap and I relished the chance to nerd out about beer again. I talked at length with an local couple about the area and got to know the bartender a little bit, who'd moved away from Cape Breton as a girl only be able to fully appreciate when she moved back as an adult. All of them were more than happy to listen to my enthusiastic, effusive rambling about my trip. I picked up a growler of their sour IPA (stellar, like magical fruit elixir) to take home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alas, things must come to an end and after only a precious two hours at the brewery I was back in the shuttle on my to Halifax again. Now, sitting in the train on my way back to Toronto, I write up my experience so that others may enjoy it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="The steed at trip's end" src="images/bigspruce.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The steed at trip's end&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

</content></entry><entry><title>5 Tips on Completing a PhD</title><link href="/5-tips-on-completing-a-phd.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-04-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-04-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Neurosponge</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-04-24:/5-tips-on-completing-a-phd.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't piss off your advisor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A very wise man on his graduation shared these five lessons with me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't piss off your advisor; play the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn patience; experiments will fail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explore as much as you can while in school. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try to remember why you liked science before starting a PhD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn quantitative methods; the future of biology is not going to be just biology. &lt;em&gt;Learn to code&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He now has the best job in the world building artificial intelligence for Google, so I try to follow these lessons as closely as possible.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>When research doesn't seem to work out</title><link href="/when-research-doesnt-seem-to-work-out.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-04-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2015-04-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Neurosponge</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-04-01:/when-research-doesnt-seem-to-work-out.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I just got the results back from an experiment. It wasn't good.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I just got the results back from an experiment that was supposed to form the backbone of my thesis. It wasn't good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experiment involved the CLARITY technique, which is an advanced method of making organic tissue transparent and, which it turns out, is a son of a bitch to actually make work. The specifics aren't important, but basically, there's a lot of trouble-shooting that needs to be done and I am not allowed to do it because the technique can only be performed by one of the senior postdocs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This made me realize something about the nature of working in science. Projects fail all the time. If we're being honest with ourselves, poking complex biological systems with random ideas should always turn out more dead ends than positive results. Unfortunately, it's not possible to survive as a researcher earnestly spinning out null results. Thus, an important skill to have is to be able continually reexamine your project as it proceeds, keeping track of how likely it is to turn into something good, and how to pivot away from it if things stop working. In a way, maybe a good researcher has to be a lot like a good entrepreneur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm stuck with the unfortunate prospect of trying to pivot a project that already sits at a pretty low position in the hierarchy of projects at the lab. I'm not personally distraught, but looking forward to the challenge. Even though it involves the end of something, it's going to mean change. And that's what I've been craving lately.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>TV Screens on Airplanes</title><link href="/tv-screens-on-airplanes.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2014-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Neurosponge</name></author><id>tag:None,2014-05-15:/tv-screens-on-airplanes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After boarding a United Airlines aircraft, waiting your turn to shamble down the cramped aisles, overhead pressing your engorged carry on into the overhead compartment, and settling down in your assigned seat with the hope of finally being able to relax, you may find yourself greeted by the fleshy faces of old white men animatedly expressing urgent political opinions at you from an 8-inch screen positioned directly in front of your face.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After boarding a United Airlines aircraft, waiting your turn to shamble down the cramped aisles, overhead pressing your engorged carry on into the overhead compartment, and settling down in your assigned seat with the hope of finally being able to relax, you may find yourself greeted by the fleshy faces of old white men animatedly expressing urgent political opinions at you from an 8-inch screen positioned directly in front of your face. It’s what I encountered when trying to fly from Seattle to Orlando last winter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine my surprise when, sitting down into the seat that was to become my airborne cradle for the next four hours, I beheld a room of newscasters theatrically debating the President's actions in muted silence. The show's title, FACE THE NATION, which was not only displayed in all caps on the bottom left of the screen, but also printed on the oligarchic figures' matching coffee mugs seemed especially poetic considering my confined state.
Face the nation. Certainly, I had no choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I eventually found a way to turn off the screen (the dimmer button, when taken to it’s extreme, usually works), but was appalled when it roared back to life after the safety demonstration to display another United Airlines commercial spot. It continued to do this throughout the flight – me turning it off, and it coming back to life to show me the same 2014 Olympics United Airlines spot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Travelling by plane nowadays is an experience in the worst aspects of American culture. After having your privacy invaded at the security checkpoints, you are let loose into a monotonous causeway of branded storefronts. Furthermore, with frequent delays, even your freedom to determine how much time you spend in these gaudy surroundings is lost. With the inclusion of these seat-mounted TV screens, the last vestige of privacy, seclusion, and nobility is being invaded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Granted, these screens can be a welcome sight to the traveler who does not bring his own entertainment, and I can understand how many passengers would prefer the mind-dulling pleasure of scanning through the latest episodes of Modern Family to the meditative, but frustrating and mind-dulling experience of trying to sleep in an airline seat. However, I have noticed that the degree to which these screens are enjoyable is directly proportional to how much control one has over them. Indeed, on a recent Air Canada flight, said screen became my fast friend due to its vast library of free movies and music (Bright Eyes? How swell) and its limited commercial interruptions. Airlines should keep in mind the incredible anxiety that can be created when people aren't able to maintain a small degree of control over their surroundings (how much do you think I was able to recline in this chair?). Also, its time they put more outlets in planes. There is a unique sense of doom that is created when you realize you're sitting down for a nine hour flight and you only have 30 minutes of battery life on your laptop.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Neuroscience on a Vipassana Retreat</title><link href="/neuroscience-on-a-vipassana-retreat.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-04-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2014-04-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Neurosponge</name></author><id>tag:None,2014-04-28:/neuroscience-on-a-vipassana-retreat.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wish someone had warned me about the chanting. Every meditation begins with Goenka reciting Buddhist scripture in a long, low, loud, crumbly drone that fails to adhere to any standards of tonality. Musically, it is very, very bad.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After escaping University with my diploma in neuroscience, I decided to use some of my newly-earned freedom to study the mind from a different perspective. I had heard from several friends about “hardcore” Vipassana retreats that were available by donation to people who wanted to study meditation and thought I might try one in order to further my own meditation practice. My experience ended up being more intense, transformative, and intellectually interesting than I could have imagined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Vipassana Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Vipassana retreat is a rigorously structured, 10-day, silent meditation course taught entirely by the audio and video recordings of SN Goenka, a businessman-turned-Buddhist teacher who popularized a certain style of Burmese meditation. Each retreat is essentially a crash course in meditation and Buddhist Philosophy, though it sometimes feels like an induction into a jolly Indian ghost's personal army of mind-soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a way, a Vipassana retreat is a lot like the summer camp you may have gone to as a kid: you head off into the wilderness, live in gender-specific dorms, eat in a mess hall, and can't leave. The big difference is that the only thing you do at this camp is meditate (about 11 hours a day). There is no talking, no exercising, no meals after noon, just meditation, stretching, drinking tea, walking in the woods, and brushing your teeth. This is quite a radical way to spend one's time and may lead to profound introspection, intense psychological strain, and a whole assortment of weird trance states. For me, it was a fascinating exercise in studying the brain 'from the inside out' and a fruitful opportunity to reappraise habits, strengthen some cognitive abilities, and sort out girl problems. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I arrived at the center, I was asked whether I knew what I was getting in to and if I would commit to staying for the whole ten days. The accommodations were nice and the people reassuringly placid, so I consented. Shortly thereafter, all the students gathered in the dining hall -- all different ages, all white, all drinking tea and awaiting the first sitting. The ladies chatted animatedly in their corner, like they'd known each other for years. Us men just sat, murmuring between sips of roobois and hoping the enforced silence would make things less awkward. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the chanting began. I wish someone had warned me about the chanting. Every meditation begins with Goenka reciting Buddhist scripture in a long, low, loud, crumbly drone that fails to adhere to any standards of tonality. Musically, it is very, very bad. However, I soon came to appreciate the chanting, finding it soothing and helpful for meditation (it took a couple days). The resonant sound fills the room and provides a good atmosphere for relaxation while the exotic otherworldliness really makes you feel like you doing something ancient and eminently spiritual. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went to bed that first night not sure what to think. I had survived an evening of sitting still, but I certainly didn't feel any different. Little did I know that the next ten days would be a fucking roller-coaster ride of emotions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Life on Retreat&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first day was simple, slow, and boring. We began with breath meditation and I spent the entire day trying to focus on my nostrils. My mind was scattered and the meditation never seemed to go anywhere. Time dragged by agonizingly slowly, but I was impressed by the quality of the food and how good all the other students were at avoiding eye contact. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I awoke the next morning acutely aware of the fact that I had to spend nine more days in this purgatory. I slept through the morning meditation period, preferring the entertainment of my dreams to the tedium of the cushion. Eventually, I reminded myself why I was there and dragged myself back to meditation. My mind appeared to be just as scattered the day before; however, by that evening I began to feel the first inkling of a deep sense of calm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great source of distraction that I grappled with during these first few days was dreaming. In the absence of any stimulation during the day, I noticed that my dream recall was vastly improved. Thus, my dreams became the most action-packed part of my day; I got to see friends, fight giant spiders, and fly around like a demi-god. I started napping as much as possible until I discovered this strategy's significant downsides: grumpiness and grogginess. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the third day, a floodgate opened up in my psyche. I had been battling distraction since I showed up, but now the thoughts which clamored for my attention became harsh, vivid and personal. Trying to focus on the breath felt like trying to conn a ship in a hurricane. Memories rushed to the surface, beginning with recent events and progressing backwards in time until visions of childhood toys that I had not thought about for years began spontaneously arising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At times, the inability to control my own my mind made me incredibly anxious. As my internal dialogue fragmented and voices in my head began berating me, the discomfort in my knees and back from maintaining proper posture became searing pain. I could see how mental and physical discomfort amplify each other. During these stressful moments, I observed that the contents of my spontaneously arising thoughts became very predictable. Thoughts about sex and, of all things, video games would race through my mind. I cam to understand that my mind was grasping for familiar sources of escape and sensual gratification in order to escape the discomfort of the present moment. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite how disturbing and uncontrollable these episodes were, they always came to an end. Often, I would sit through bouts of mental anguish, bombarded by horrifyingly graphic sexual imagery, only to end the meditation session in a blissful calm. During one sitting, I remember having the distinct sensation that snow was falling in the hall, covering everything in a soft, warm, blanket of silence. I came to love the routine of slipping into the stillness of meditation, greeting the lunch bell with gratitude, and walking through the hall with a pleasant, acute awareness of my body. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After four days of practicing meditation on the breath, I began to feel very comfortable with the rhythm of the retreat. I was having meals and going for walk-abouts in a meditative calm. I felt like I was getting the hang of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this was soon shattered by the introduction of the Vipassana meditation technique. The Vipassana technique as taught by Goenka involves proceduraly passing one's attention through the body, starting with focusing on the “top of the head” and moving down to the “tips of the toes.” At the end of the introductory two-hour meditation, I felt wrenched out of my body, curiously aware that I was observing the actions of a clunky, fleshy body from a precarious position somewhere outside of it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This style of meditation felt more cognitively demanding than breath meditiation. On top of trying to maintain concentration, now I was struggling to locate subtle sensations on my shoulders and armpits. We were also told to begin the practice of sitting Adhiṭṭhāna, without moving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, an experience I had with another meditator provided an interesting lesson in equanimity. At the beginning of the second half of the course, an elderly gentleman who normally sat several spaces in front of me moved to a chair directly behind me. Something must have made him sick because around this time he also adopted a habit of coughing, yawning, and sniffling during our sittings. So there I was, attempting to sit through pain Adhiṭṭhāna-style with this guy's mouth less than four feet away from my head, the sound of his epiglottis flapping around was channelled directly into my ear. At first, I was annoyed. Then, a hatred developed withing me that sparked a state of panicked rage everytime he made a sound. I felt ashamed about my aversion, but how could he do this to me? Didn't he have any respect? Trying to ignore the sounds didn't work. I couldn't be equanimous. Eventually, I could feel my body tensing up with amygdala-flavored stress before the sounds even had the opportunity to consciously register in my mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a breakthrough when I stopped trying to ignore the sound and instead consciously reacted to it with empathy and compassion. Once I was able to replace the anger with love just once, I noticed the effect snowball until it become unconscious. Although there was some backsliding along the way, by unpairing the sound with feelings of enger, I eventually ended up rewiring my response to be positive rather than negative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Meditation and the Brain&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout all of this, I was intensely curious about what this meditation was doing to my brain. Goenka's nightly talks explained that we were learning to control our minds and cultivate non-attachment and selflessness. I was becoming more comfortable with these ideas, but the scientist within me wanted to go deeper. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientific research on meditation has exploded in the last couple years, but the field is still filled with contention and murkiness (see &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HKxK9YTaTgA"&gt;this awesome video&lt;/a&gt; for a glimpse of how complex the cognitive neuroscience of meditation has become). In order to avoid getting too academic or too inaccurate, I'll only discuss some of the key neuroscientific findings that relate to my experience on retreat (for an in-depth review on what is known, see Vago and Silbersweig 2012).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to neuroimaging, there is now growing body of evidence linking meditation to physical changes in the brain such as increased cortical volume (Lazar et al. 2005), white matter connectivity (Tang et al. 2012), and cortical gyrification (Luders et al. 2012). Furthermore, other research has described the benefits of meditation on domains such as attention (Hodgins and Adair 2010) and mood (Khoury et al. 2013). The story that the research describes is this: meditation activates brain regions underlying abilities like concentration and emotional regulation and, over time, strengthens these abilities through experience dependent neuroplasticity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three basic types of meditation taught within Buddhism and each techniqued has been studied more less independently and shown to induce a specific pattern of activation in the brain, which leads to specific benefits of long-term practice. On the retreat, I was impressed to discover that these different forms of meditation lead to vastly different subjective experiences and qualities of mind that stayed with me once I left the cushion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anapana or breath meditation, where one focuses intensely on the breath, is a classic form of concentration meditation that has been shown to recruit the attentional subprocesses of alerting, orienting, and executive control, each of which appears to be mediated by a different region of the brain (Manna et al. 2010; Raz and Buhle 2006). Meditating on my breath for hours at a time, I swear I could almost see my attention deconstructed into these different subsystems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the retreat progressed, I noticed a significant improvement in my ability to direct my attention. I was able to go for walks and eat meals without losing track of the breath. I witnessed an entire sunset without getting distracted or bored. Indeed. enhanced attentional control has been demonstrated in experienced meditators, who perform better on the famous &lt;a href="http://faculty.washington.edu/chudler/java/ready.html"&gt;Stroop Test&lt;/a&gt; (5,9)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strengthening these attentional subsystems may be beneficial for reasons beyond increasing the ability to focus. For example, activity in the attention network has also shown that activity in the brain networks that underlie focused awareness, inhibit activity in the brain's default network (Fox et al. 2005). The default network is thought to be involved in day-dreaming and self-referential thinking (ie. "I should have applied for that internship," "That coffee made me tired", "I'm not the type of guy she's in to"). Over-activity in this network is thought to underlie the ruminative bummer thoughts that are a core feature of depression (Smallwood and O’Connor 2011). The relationship between meditation and decreased activity in this netwok is one of the most compelling explanations for how it may increase well-being (Brewer et al. 2011). Furthermore, cultivating the ability to be aware of one's own attention may be helpful in disentangling environmental triggers from habitual behaviour patterns, such as I was able to do with the old guy's yawns (Hodgins and Adair 2010). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, concentration meditation in the Vipassana tradition is only seen as a stepping stone. The real meat of the retreat is the Vipassana body-scanning technique that is taught as a way to develop panna, wisdom born of self-awareness and equanimity. Panna may be manifested in the increased well-being and resistance to stress seen in long-term meditators (Brown and Ryan 2003; Mohan et al., Bijlani 2011). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What sprang to my mind while I was painstakingly performing the body scans (besides how cool it would be to image my somatosensory cortex activity), was what I read about the effect of long-term meditation on grey matter density in the insula (Hölzel et al. 2008). The insula is an interesting  region of the cerebral cortex that lies deep in the brain and has connections to the frontal cortex, somatosensory cortex, and mid-brain regions involved in mood. The interesting thing about the insula is that it is organized such that its posterior regions regulate awareness of low-level phenomena like heartbeat and bodily sensations, while its anterior portion is involved in awareness of higher-level phenomena such as emotions and motivational states (Critchley et al. 2004). It's possible that the insula could be where body sensations integrate with subjective feeling states, mediating a bidirectional interaction between somatic sensations and emotions. Basically, the insula may control how the world makes us feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If multiple forms of self-awareness are processed in the same place, it may mean that simply observing body sensations will lead to improvements in the awareness and regulation of other internal phenomenon. Perhaps due to shared neural circuitry in the insula or the spill-over effects of a local growth stimulus, there might be a physiological basis for the efficacy of body meditation to improve  one's ability to control how they respond to the stresses and discomforts of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final type of meditation taught on the retreat is metta, or loving-kindness meditation. The practice involves arousing and broadcasting kindness and has been shown to increase activity in mood and empathy-related areas (Lutz et al. 2008). In my experience, the practice almost always leads to tremor-inducing feelings of warmth and compassion. Interestingly, long-term loving-kindness practice is associated with larger cortical volume at the tempoparietal junction, the area of the brain shown to be crucial for theory of mind and social cognition (Holzel et al. 2011; Sowden and Catmur 2013). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current state of research suggests a story: frequent activation of brain regions during meditation increases the volume of these areas and improves their function. In this way, the brain could be expected to function much like a muscle. In order to see functional improvements in attention, self-control, and mood, one woud need to perform continous, challenging exercise. Furthermore, in order to maintain these improvements, the exercise needs to be maintained. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the risk of sounding like a "scientific materialistic," I would suggest that the meditation I did on retreat was essentially a workout for a handful of different brain networks. By focusing on my breath, I strengthened my attentional networks. By scanning my body, I strengthened my insula's capacity for self-regulation, and by practicing loving-kindness, I exercised the regions of my brain responsible for feeling compassion. Although this a gross over-simplification, meditation did wasn't much different than going to the gym to work out my muscles. Like muscles, I believe that these networks require consistent, challenging exercise in order to become stronger, and furthermore, that they require continual training in order to maintain the benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Vipassana in Life&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I arrived back in the real world, I felt incredibly peaceful, disciplined, and content. Observing the business of the city, I felt a little bit of a child-like wonder.  My laptop felt like some kind of cryptic object, I loved that. Many of the retreat's benefits withered in the weeks following the retreat, as I stopped making time to meditate and became reacquainted with stress, over-stimulation, and booze. Absolutely, I believe that the benefits of meditation are “dose-dependent.” Since I have settled down and returned to my practice, I've noticed inklings of that deep peace coming back to me. My meditations go deeper and faster than they ever did before the retreat. I guess it's like a riding a bike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are considering attending a retreat, I encourage you to go. Some parts of it will be really fucking hard in a way you may have never experienced in your life. However, it'll all be balanced out by the positive, such is life. You'll learn more about yourself in the process and come out feeling vastly different than you did going in. It will be a rich experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am considering going back for another round when the timing works out. A retreat once a year seems to be a good opportunity to clear your headspace and make sure you're headed down the right track. Besides, it was a lot of &lt;a href="http://kellycordes.wordpress.com/2009/11/02/the-fun-scale/"&gt;fun&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Citations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brewer, Judson A., Patrick D. Worhunsky, Jeremy R. Gray, et al.
 2011   Meditation Experience Is Associated with Differences in Default Mode Network Activity and Connectivity. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences: 201112029.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brown, Kirk Warren, and Richard M. Ryan
 2003   The Benefits of Being Present: Mindfulness and Its Role in Psychological Well-Being. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology 84(4): 822–848.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critchley, Hugo D., Stefan Wiens, Pia Rotshtein, Arne Öhman, and Raymond J. Dolan
 2004   Neural Systems Supporting Interoceptive Awareness. Nature Neuroscience 7(2): 189–195.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fox, Michael D, Abraham Z Snyder, Justin L Vincent, et al.
 2005   The Human Brain Is Intrinsically Organized into Dynamic, Anticorrelated Functional Networks. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 102(27): 9673–9678.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hodgins, Holley S, and Kathryn C Adair
 2010   Attentional Processes and Meditation. Consciousness and Cognition 19(4): 872–878.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holzel, Britta K., James Carmody, Mark Vangel, et al.
 2011   Mindfulness Practice Leads to Increases in Regional Brain Gray Matter Density. Psychiatry Research 191(1): 36–43.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hölzel, Britta K., Ulrich Ott, Tim Gard, et al.
 2008   Investigation of Mindfulness Meditation Practitioners with Voxel-Based Morphometry. Social Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience 3(1): 55–61.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Khoury, Bassam, Tania Lecomte, Guillaume Fortin, et al.
 2013   Mindfulness-Based Therapy: A Comprehensive Meta-Analysis. Clinical Psychology Review 33(6): 763–771.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lazar, Sara W., Catherine E. Kerr, Rachel H. Wasserman, et al.
 2005   Meditation Experience Is Associated with Increased Cortical Thickness. Neuroreport 16(17): 1893–1897.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luders, Eileen, Florian Kurth, Emeran A Mayer, et al.
 2012   The Unique Brain Anatomy of Meditation Practitioners: Alterations in Cortical Gyrification. Frontiers in Human Neuroscience 6: 34.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lutz, Antoine, Julie Brefczynski-Lewis, Tom Johnstone, and Richard J. Davidson
 2008   Regulation of the Neural Circuitry of Emotion by Compassion Meditation: Effects of Meditative Expertise. PLoS ONE 3(3): e1897.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manna, Antonietta, Antonino Raffone, Mauro Gianni Perrucci, et al.
 2010   Neural Correlates of Focused Attention and Cognitive Monitoring in Meditation. Brain Research Bulletin 82(1-2): 46–56.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mohan, Amit, Ratna Sharma, and Ramesh L. Bijlani
 2011   Effect of Meditation on Stress-Induced Changes in Cognitive Functions. The Journal of Alternative and Complementary Medicine 17(3): 207–212.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raz, Amir, and Jason Buhle
 2006   Typologies of Attentional Networks. Nature Reviews Neuroscience 7(5): 367–379.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smallwood, Jonathan, and Rory C O’Connor
 2011   Imprisoned by the Past: Unhappy Moods Lead to a Retrospective Bias to Mind Wandering. Cognition &amp;amp; Emotion 25(8): 1481–1490.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sowden, Sophie, and Caroline Catmur
 2013   The Role of the Right Temporoparietal Junction in the Control of Imitation. Cerebral Cortex: bht306.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tang, Yi-Yuan, Qilin Lu, Ming Fan, Yihong Yang, and Michael I. Posner
 2012   Mechanisms of White Matter Changes Induced by Meditation. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences: 201207817.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vago, David R., and David A. Silbersweig
 2012   Self-Awareness, Self-Regulation, and Self-Transcendence (S-ART): A Framework for Understanding the Neurobiological Mechanisms of Mindfulness. Frontiers in Human Neuroscience 6. http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3480633/, accessed October 10, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Fractionating Human Intelligence</title><link href="/fractionating-human-intelligence.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-04-23T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2014-04-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Neurosponge</name></author><id>tag:None,2014-04-23:/fractionating-human-intelligence.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine recently drew my attention to &lt;a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0896627312005843"&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt; regarding the neural systems of general intelligence. Besides reminding me of my only time attempting to measure my IQ (taking the long-invalidated Tickle.com test at 13 years old while my mom yelled at me from the kitchen), this formidable piece of science had me thinking about how difficult it really is to quantify something as complex, plastic, and context-dependent as intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine recently drew my attention to &lt;a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0896627312005843"&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt; regarding the neural systems of general intelligence. Besides reminding me of my only time attempting to measure my IQ (taking the long-invalidated Tickle.com test at 13 years old while my mom yelled at me from the kitchen), this formidable piece of science had me thinking about how difficult it really is to quantify something as complex, plastic, and context-dependent as intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, the classic theory of IQ is getting a little outdated. Psychologists in the early twentieth century developed the idea of a generalized factor of intelligence based on the finding that performance was correlated across many different types of cognitive tasks. With the aid of fMRI and principal component analysis, &lt;a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0896627312005843"&gt;this interesting pape&lt;/a&gt; attempts to answer the question of whether IQ has a distinct neural correlate or is an artifact of the interaction between multiple specialized systems? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the paper goes into some pretty advanced statistical modelling that I won't be able to cover, but there were some general highlights that I found very interesting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The areas of the brain that are activated during different cognitive tests can be divided into areas specifically related to working memory (WM) and reasoning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Variability in IQ test scores can best be explained by modelling intelligence as the result of multiple factors (working memory, reasoning, verbal)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was a small positive association between working memory and reasoning performance and frequency of computer gaming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;individuals who suffered from anxiety had slightly lower working memory scores&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Differences between men and women on the cognitive tests were negligible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alcohol and caffeine consumption had a negligible effect on cognitive performance
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link to the full study: &lt;a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0896627312005843"&gt;Fractionating Human Intelligence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Protein Intake and Aging</title><link href="/protein-intake-and-aging.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-03-05T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2014-03-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Neurosponge</name></author><id>tag:None,2014-03-05:/protein-intake-and-aging.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A new study on the relationship between protein intake and longevity has been making the rounds across the internet. The impressive &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24606898"&gt;16-author paper&lt;/a&gt; from the Longo Laba at USC is not the first to suggest that meat is bad for you, but it does seem to be rather well supported than the rest, with a cellular and molecular component and even a handful of yeast experiments thrown in.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A new study on the relationship between protein intake and longevity has been making the rounds across the internet. The impressive &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24606898"&gt;16-author paper&lt;/a&gt; from the Longo Laba at USC is not the first to suggest that meat is bad for you, but it does seem to be rather well supported than the rest, with a cellular and molecular component and even a handful of yeast experiments thrown in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By analyzing data from an American cross-sectional health survey, the authors found that adults between the ages of 50 and 65 who obtained over 10% of their calories from protein had shorter lifespans and were more likely to die from cancer, diabetes, and cardiovascular disease than those who consumed less than 10% of their calories from protein. This effect was greatest in the group that consumed over 20% of their calories from protein, who were found to be four times more likely to die from cancer than those in the low-protein group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, this association only held true for animal protein. The proportion of plant-based protein, carbohydrates, and fat in people's diets did not seem to hold any correlation to mortality based on this data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely, protein intake appeared to have the opposite effect in those over the age of 65. Higher protein intake was associated with decreased overall and cancer mortality. The author's believe that this may be due to a decrease in protein absorption and the need to consume higher levels of protein in order to maintain normal body weight and function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to understand the basis for relationship between meat and mortality, the authors examined blood test data from a subset of the study population. They found that the concentration of IGF-1 (essentialy growth hormone), was proportional to protein intake. Statistical tests found that, although IGF-1 levels did not mediate the association between protein intake and mortality, they were a significant moderator of the effect. This means that there was still an independent effect of protein intake on mortality when IGF-1 levels were controlled for. However, variation in IGF-1 levels appeared to influence the strength of the relationship. So, if IGF-1 isn't the complete story, the authors concluded that it at least plays a large role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors then ran some mice experiments to observe how protein intake and IGF-1 might influence cancer mortality. They implanted tumors into mice and found that they grew larger and faster in mice on a high protein diet. Contradicting the human data, this effect appeared in mice fed both animal and plant-based protein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mice team then turned their sights towards IGF-1. Compared to mice on a high protein diet (18%), Mice on a low protein diet had 35% less IGF-1 than those on a high protein diet and higher levels of IGF binding protein, which inhibits the action of IGF-1 in the blood. Furthermore, tumor progression was greatly inhibited in a strain of mice that lacked the IGF-1 receptor. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this perfect evidence that a vegetarian diet is best for optimal longevity? No, but it does have significant strengths over some &lt;a href="http://archinte.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleid=1134845" title="Title"&gt;previous&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://archinte.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleid=414881" title="Title"&gt;studies&lt;/a&gt;.  Most notably, the mice experiments allow this paper to go beyond the common limitations of cross-sectional studies and link human data to an already existing body of research linking &lt;a href="http://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736%2804%2916044-3/fulltext"&gt;cancer proliferation and IGF-1 signaling&lt;/a&gt; . It also draws its epidemiological data from a sensible place, the Third National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANESIII), which collected data from participants by having them track everything they ate over a 24hr period, rather than having them make guesses about their eating habits. It also processed that data sensibly, controlling for the myriad factors that might counfound things: age, race/ethnicity, education, sex, disease status, smoking, dietary changes, total calorie consumption, and even waist circumference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this paper still only points to an association. The different effects of protein consumption between those over and under 65 is especially curious. Also, if age had such a strong effect on protein and cancer risk, it should be possible to analyze age as a covariable, identifying the relationship between age and the protein-mortality interaction along a linear regression. Instead, the authors simply split the population up into two groups, supposedly because that was the best way to get a significant effect out of the data. Furthermore, the number of people in the low-protein group was very low, only around 1/10th of the number in any of the other groups. This increases the chance that the sample is not representative of the population -- not the basis of good &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, the most curious part of this story is the relationship between &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8156941"&gt;protein and IGF-1&lt;/a&gt;. In the human data, it appeared to be meat in particular that mediated the increased cancer risk, but in the animal data, soy protein lead to similar increases in IGF-1 and cancer growth. At least one previous study has suggested that the IGF-1 increase due to protein intake is due to essential amino acids, which are found in &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16201743"&gt;greater concentrations&lt;/a&gt; in animal protein. Interestingly, restricton of one of these amino acids, methionine, has been linked to &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8001743"&gt;increased lifespan in mice&lt;/a&gt;. This is far from being completely understoond, but is interesting to think about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been travelling a lot frequently and that means eating on the cheap, sometimes without the ability to cook. That puts meat out of the question in a lot of cases and so I've significantly cut back. Perhaps I should keep this streak going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link to the full study: &lt;a href="http://www.cell.com/cell-metabolism/fulltext/S1550-4131%2814%2900062-X" title="Title"&gt;Low Protein Intake Is Associated with a Major Reduction in IGF-1, Cancer, and Overall Mortality...&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>No Choice</title><link href="/no-choice.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-02-01T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2014-02-01T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Neurosponge</name></author><id>tag:None,2014-02-01:/no-choice.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tonight a met a man who has lived a very different life than I. After experiencing a heart attack at a weight of around 350 lbs, he realized that he would either change everything about his life style or die in 3 years. He was at risk of getting type …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tonight a met a man who has lived a very different life than I. After experiencing a heart attack at a weight of around 350 lbs, he realized that he would either change everything about his life style or die in 3 years. He was at risk of getting type II diabetes in his thirties and had begun to experience numbness in his legs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, it wasn't all this guy's fault. Apparently, he was found to have have a basal metabolic rate (BMR) of only 1200 calories a day (the normal for an adult male is around 2400). His body naturally burned about half as many calories as a normal person, so even with a normal caloric intake, he would have to work out like a competitive athelete just to maintain his bodyweight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With no choice, he began taking his life into his own hands. 7 days a week, he would get up at 5am and cycle, lift weights, and run for 4 hours. This was on top of working a job at IBM and raising 2 kids. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite being dealt the shittiest of hands, this guy created the determination to do what he had to do for himself and his family. In his case, fear was the motivator that allowed him to change his life. He admitted to me that absolutely hates lifting weights, but he still does it and has changed his life because of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine what you could do if you took 4 hours of your day to work at something with life-or-death intensity. &lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>